Hello, this is Dr. Dong-Zan.
In this lecture,
we'll discuss the
metabolism of
cholesterol and bio acid.
So this slide shows you all the
learning objectives
about this lecture.
And basically, the first
part of the lecture
focusing on the
metabolism of cholesterol,
and the second part
of the lecture,
we're focusing on the
metabolism of bioacid.
First, we want to
discuss briefly about the
structure and physiological
function of cholesterols.
Cholesterol often
get a bad rap.
We all know that too much
cholesterol is not good.
But on the other hand,
the cholesterol, they
do have important
physiological
functions. For example,
they are a component of many
of the cellular membranes.
They can function
to modulate the so
-called fluidity of the
cellular membranes.
In addition,
the cholesterol is
also a precursor for a
variety of important
biomolecules, for example,
vitamin D,
sterile hormones,
or bioacid. And although
many tissue organs
can synthesize
cholesterols, but liver
is the most important
organs that play a
critical role in the
cholesterol homostasis.
The structure of cholesterol
contains a so-called
sterile nucleus, right?
For the steronucleus, it's
basically four big ring
molecules linked together,
the ring names ABCD.
And also, as you can see here,
all the carbons for the
steronucleus are numbered.
You certainly don't
need to memorize all
the structure, but there's
a couple of important
carbon positions
that we'll refer to
the steroids right ol
means it contains hydroxy
group so steroids are
a subclass of steroids
that always contain
a hydroxy group at
carbon three right
here's the carbon three
and also aliphatic chains and
can link to the carbon 17s
also the hydroxy group
at carbon 3 can be
easterfied right so
the carboxyl as carboxy
containing molecule can
attach to this hydroxy
group in addition for the
cholesterol it also contain
a double bond between
carbon-5 and carbon-6.
And a couple of
additional nomenclature
related to steroids
and the sterols.
You know, sometimes you
see a Greek letter alpha,
that usually indicating
a group that is below the
plane of the rings, right?
And also, you know, in
the structure, they also
indicated as dashed lines.
Another great letter beta
often indicating
that a particular
group is above the planes.
And the beta conformation
in the structure usually
indicated by solid lines.
And for the Greek letter
dirta, that is indicating
molecule contain double
bonds and the position
of the double bond
indicating by numbers.
For example,
again, for the cholesterols,
it has a double bond between
carbon-6 and carbon-5.
So the first major
function of cholesterol
is the key component
for the membrane, right
regulating the membrane
and fluidity as you
probably already know
the major component of
various membrane are
phospholipids right phospholipid
is an amphipathic molecule
as a polar side which
is because the phosphate group
and also has a hydrophobic
side has the uh long
you know uh hydrophobic
tails and as indicating
this diagram right you know
large majority of the
membrane uh phospholipid the
polar side facing the water
and the hydrophobic side
facing internally and you
can uh sporadically find
cholesterol molecules right
it's a hydroxy group again
facing the aqueous side and
the hydrophobic ring part
of the cholesterol get
buried in the hydrophobic
lipid biolayer and the
membrane structure is not
stationary there's actually
certain molecules that buried
within the membrane actually
can move around so So
therefore, cholesterol
plays a key part in terms of
regulating the fluidity
of various cell membranes.
Again, the second major
function of cholesterol is a
precursor for a variety of
biomolecules. For example,
vitamin D, its structure
is shown here, from
the bottom part of
the vitamin B, D, you
can make out, you know,
that looks like the
rain structure of
cholesterol, right? Indeed,
that this part of the
molecule of vitamin D
is come from the
sternucleus, right? As you
probably know, that
vitamin D play a critical
role for the calcium
metabolism, and we'll
go into more detail in
the vitamin lectures.
So either way,
vitamin D can, you know,
we can synthesize vitamin D
in the skin. When the skin
is exposed to UV lights, it
can convert the cholesterols
into vitamin D molecules.
And cholesterol is also
an important precursor for
quite a few sterile
hormones, right, for example,
progesterone, testosterone,
estradiol, or estrogen,
or cortisones, right. You
can look at these structures,
you know, they're quite
similar, I'll remind you
of the sterile nucleus,
right, that come from the
cholesterol, again, you
know, these different sterile
hormones utilize cholesterol
and utilizing a different
enzyme, a variety of pathway
way to synthesize them.
And this slide summarizes
a few genetic diseases
that are related to the
sterile hormone biosynthesis.
And when you encounter
these different diseases
in different subjects
of your curriculum,
and you can always come
back and review how these
different hormones are
synthesized from cholesterols
and finally cholesterol is
also the precursor for bile
acid you'll see in the
latter part of this lecture
again you know if you look
at the primary bile acid
colic acid and kinocolic
acid right has the they all
have this foreign structures
and they synthesize from
cholesterols and one of the
key enzyme seven hydroxyl
is catalyzed the re-limiting
step of bio acid again
we'll come back to this
later plants usually don't
have a whole lot of
cholesterol right but they do
have you got a similar molecules
similar to the steroids
including stigma sterile
cytosterol or cytostanol
plant steroids or
these molecules usually
they don't get absorbed
very efficiently
by our digestive system
so after the uh you
know getting to the
digestive system entering
the enterocytes enter is
the prefix for intestine
and they actually get
actively transported
back into the intestine
lumens and in the
process they actually bring
some of the cholesterol
with them right so
therefore the plant
steroids in the diet you
know can help to reduce
the absorption of the
cholesterols that in our diet.
And this slide shows the, you
know, structures
for Cetosterol,
for Stigma Sterol, and for
Cetostanos. As you can see,
their absorption rate
is all in the single
digit. And in comparison,
reducing the absorption
rate for cholesterols
can go as high as 33%.
In general, for a
healthy individual,
the amount of cholesterol in
our body is often in a balance.
So you can have
cholesterol come from your
diet, it comes from
the de novo synthesis
in the liver, and
also can, you know,
the cholesterol
can be picked up
from the actual hepatic tissues
and through the HDL or
high-density lipoprotein
and transport them
back into the liver.
And, you know, for the
cholesterols that are produced
in the liver, right, it can
get secreted or transported
to different tissue organs
through the very low
-density lipoprotein, the free
cholesterol can be secreted
into the bile as part of
the bile it can also be used
to synthesize the bile salt
as again you will see later
on so for a typical Western
diet it usually contains
you know four hundred to
six hundred milligrams
cholesterol per day about half
of us get absorbed and this
This absorption is mediated
by a protein called Neiman
-PKC1-like-1 protein, in
short for MPC1L1. And this is
actually the target for a
cholesterol-reducing drug,
azetima.
And about 800 milligrams
per day of cholesterol,
you know, we can
synthesize it by ourself.
And this production is
balanced by the excretion
of bioacid. Again,
you know, a lot of the
cholesterol can be used
for the bioacid synthesis.
And as you can see the,
you know, the influx and
outflux of the cholesterol,
you can figure out a way,
you know, if you need to
control the cholesterol level,
right, there's a couple
strategies you can decrease
the cholesterol level in
the body. For example,
you know, by reducing the
cholesterol in your diet,
or decrease the cholesterol
biosynthesis from our own
body or increase the
excretion of bio acid you know
all these different strategies
can help you achieve
the goal of reducing the
cholesterol in the blood
all right now we uh going
to discuss uh some uh
aspect of the biosynthesis
of cholesterol right and
you'll see this slides
before when we study uh
different metabolic pathways
right this is basically
guide you how to study any
metabolic pathways right
so you need to know
what's the purpose what's
the importance of the
pathway and what are the
committed or re-limiting or
e-revolve reactions or steps
and the enzyme involved
in those steps because
these are the steps
often highly regulated
right you know that's
the regulation of the
different metabolic
pathway and obviously any
clinical correlation
that you need to know
so most tissue and organs
they can actually synthesize
you know certain amount
of cholesterols but again
liver is the major organ
that synthesize cholesterols
And similar to other
metabolic pathway, the
metabolism of cholesterol
is also highly regulated.
And, you know, the
biosynthesis of cholesterol
can be divided into
a couple of stages.
We're focusing on stage one.
In stage one, it
synthesizes a very
important precursor
for cholesterol.
It's called mevalonate.
Basically, all the
carbons in the cholesterol
molecule come from acetyl
-CoA, which you saw before.
And cholesterol biosynthesis is
mainly taking place
in the psiloplasm.
As you recall,
mitochondria is the
major organelles that
converting a lot of carbon
molecules to acetyl-CoA.
So, therefore, it
takes advantage of the
citratransport system
to transport excess
acetylcholine from mitochondria
into the psiloplasm
for cholesterol and
other lipid biosynthesis.
So, for stage one, the
first step is combine
two acetyl-CoA
molecules into acetyl
-acetyl-CoA. And this
step, or this reaction,
is catalyzed by the
enzyme called thiolase.
Movalinate is a 6-carbon
intermediate, right,
for the, within the
acetyl-CoA, only
2-carbons get
transferred at a time.
So combined 2
-acetyl-CoA producing
4-carbon acetyl
-acetyl-CoA, right,
and in the second step,
salicylic HMG-CoA synthase
basically combines one
molecule of acetoacetyl
-CoA with another molecule
of acetyl-CoA and
producing this molecule
called beta-hydroxyOH,
beta-methyl-gluryl
-CoA, right in short
for HMG-CoA right
again this reaction
is catalyzed by the
HMG-CoA synthase
and in order to produce
imabalinate HMG-CoA need to
be reduced by the enzyme
called HMG-CoA reductase
right so HMG-CoA reductase
actually catalyze the re
-limiting step for cholesterol
biosynthesis. Therefore,
this is the case step for
cholesterol regulations.
In addition, because there's
a reduction reaction,
you need two molecules of
NADPH. Again, don't confuse
NADPH with NADH, right? NADH
is the electron equivalent
or also called electron
carriers. But for NADPH,
it usually involves the
reduction reactions.
Most of the reaction taking
place at the ER membrane.
Again,
the conversion, the
step catalyzed by HMG
-CoA reductase is
irreversible reaction.
And this slide can
list the rest of the
stages of cholesterol
biosynthesis you know
just so that you'll
be aware of them
you really don't need
to memorize all this
as I mentioned before
right cholesterol has a
continuing hydroxy group
and this hydroxy group can
be easterfized right
and this easterization
reaction is catalyzed by
the enzyme called acyl-CoA
cholesterol acyltransferase,
in short for ACAT.
After esterization,
the cholesterol can be kind of
maintained or retained
inside the cells.
And in addition, cholesterol
can be secreted out as
part of the lipoprotein,
and we'll talk about it more
about it in the lipoprotein
lectures. And finally,
cholesterol can be converted
to cholesterol easter
by transferring acyl group
from phospholipid by an
enzyme called lechesine
cholesterol acyltransferase
or LCAT in high-density
lipoprotein. Again, we'll come
back to this process in
the lipoprotein lectures.
This is just to remind you
what lechocin looks like,
right, it has a phosphopolar
head, has a glycerol
scaffold, it has two free
fatty acid hydrophobic tails.
All right, so let's next
discuss a little bit
about the regulation of
cholesterol biosynthesis.
And turn out that the
regulation is relatively
complicated, right? There
are multiple mechanisms
that the cholesterol
biosynthesis can be regulated.
The first one is through
the transcription.
Obviously,
if you could make more
proteins or more enzymes
involved in the
cholesterol biosynthesis,
you can speed up or accelerate
the cholesterol biosynthesis.
Because HMG-CoA reductase
catalyze the re-limiting
step, so by regulating the
amount of HMG-CoA reductase
and you can regulate pretty
efficiently the cholesterol
biosynthesis right so
the regulation of the
transcription turned out to
be a little bit complicated uh
and first there's this
protein called steroregulatory
element binding protein and
you're short for srebp and
this is protein actually
binds this element or certain
DNA sequence called SRE.
SRE stands for steroid
response element. So when
SREBP binds to the SRE, it
can activate the transcription
of HMG chloe reductase.
The binding of SREBP
to the SRE is highly
regulated um so turn out
the srebp uh it commonly
resides at the er membrane
right so in the er
actually binds another
protein called scp stands
for srebp cleavage
activating protein right
so when the cholesterol
level is high and
cholesterol actually
combines to the scp
which basically traps
the srebp inside
the er right
preventing it to go to
going back going to the
nucleus and activating
transcription but on
the other hand when the
cholesterol level is
low the scep and srebp
complex get transported
to golgi right in golgi
the scep protein can activate
a certain protease right
the function of protease is
to cleave proteins in this
case these protease cleave
the srebp release it and
release the active dna
binding domain which then
translocate to the nucleus and
bind to the sre and activate
the transcription of genes
involving the cholesterol
biosynthesis again including
the HMGA-CoA reductase.
And the second mechanism
of regulating cholesterol
biosynthesis is through
degradation of either the
messenger RNA, right?
If you, you know, reduce
the messenger RNA, you
reduce the translation,
therefore you reduce the
amount of HMG-CoA reductase.
In addition,
the protein of HMG-CoA
reductase itself can also be
degraded, so it can target
it to the proteasome, so
the cells can reduce or
remove the HMG-CoA reductase.
In addition, the cholesterol
biosynthesis can be regulated
by phosphorylation and
dephosphorylation. Right.
In this case, again, because
HMG-CoA reductase catalyze
the reliminant step, right?
So you want to regulate
its activity through
phospholation and dephospholation.
So when energy level is low and
the AMP level is usually high.
So higher amount of
AMP binds to a protein
called AMP-activated
protein kinase, in short for
AMPK. And the binding
of AMP to AMPK activates
the kinase activity,
right? Kinase, again, adds
a phosphor group on a
target. In this case,
it adds a phosphor group
on the HMG-CoA reductase.
And as we discussed before,
that glucagon is a
mobilizing hormone, all
higher levels of steroids,
and they can also
activate AMPK, right?
Right, again, they
activate AMPK, phosphorylate
HMG-CoA reductase.
And the phosphorylation
of HMG-CoA
reductase actually
inactivates activities,
right? So therefore, slow down
the cholesterol biosynthesis.
And conversely, the
storage hormone insulin,
again, which is
usually very high after
a balanced meals uh
insulin activate of
protein phosphatase as
again as you saw before
phosphatase the function
of phosphatase is to
remove a phosphor group
from a target right in this
case it removes uh the
false group from the
hmg coeductase but it
is actually activate the
enzyme, right? So therefore,
when insulin is high,
it actually accelerates
or upregulates
the cholesterol biosynthesis.
So with that, you can add
the regulation of cholesterol
synthesis to the
list of hormonal
regulation of various
metabolic molecules,
right? For example,
For example,
mobilizing hormone, glucagon,
can upregulate glycogenolysis,
release glucose
from the glycogen,
and accelerate de
novo synthesis of
glucose, and now
you can add, it can
inhibit the cholesterol
biosynthesis.
Conversely,
when the storage hormone
is high, insulin is high,
synthesize more glycogen,
right store the glucose
and in this in our case
here it can also stimulate
cholesterol bonds and this
is also right as we're
talking about before it's
kind of a general theme that
insulin activated phosphatase
and glugogon activated
kinase but in this case
the kinase is called ampk
so this is slide summarize
what we're talking
about right you know
again Again, HMG
-CoA reductase catalyze
the re-limiting step.
There's a variety of ways
to regulate the amount
of the activity of HMG
-CoA reductase, right?
By energy, by
hormones, and lastly,
as you probably
will be aware of,
that HMG-CoA reductase
is also the molecular
target of a statin
family of drugs
in order to lower the
cholesterol levels.
All right, so now we're
going to switch gears and
discuss the biosynthesis
of bioacid. And we want
to know that, you know,
the bioacid or biosolids,
these two terms usually
are inter-exchangeable.
So we all know,
you know, again,
lipids are very hydrophobic.
They have very low solubility
in an aqueous environment,
right? So in order for
the body to better absorb
these lipids, you need
detergent, right? So
basically here, the biosauce
act as the detergent
to emulsify the different
lipids in our diet
and our bio is actually
a mixture of water
phospholipid right again
phospholipid in this case a
lechesine is the amphipathic
molecule has a polar head
has a hydrophilic tails
bioacid by salts right and
cholesterol right more or
less cholesterol hydrophobic.
Cholesterol is a precursor
to synthesized bowel salts.
Bowel salts is mainly
synthesized in the liver.
And, you know,
extra bowel salts
can be stored in
the gallbladder.
Right.
And when the bowel salts get
excreted into the
GI tract, back,
it actually can be
reabsorbed and eventually
returned to liver.
And this whole
cycle is called
androhepatic circulations.
But you know, through bile
acid, there's some of it
actually get excreted out
into the feces every day.
this could be one
of the strategies
that to lower the
cholesterol levels
all right briefly
uh go through the
synthesis of of
reactions of bio salts
uh bio salts contain
24 carbons right uh two
major one colic acid
uh kinodeoxycolic acid
again you know both has these
four big green molecules
and they actually derive
from the cholesterols
uh cholesterols contain 27
carbons right so therefore
you need to reduce or
remove three carbon from the
cholesterol molecules and
in addition uh hydrox group
are added to the sterile
core specifically at
these positions as I mentioned
you need to remove three
carbon from the adipatic
chains right so here's
the adipatic chain for the
cholesterol's shorter than
by three carbons and in
addition you know again
because cholesterol contain
a double bond this double
bond need to be reduced in
order to produce the bio
salts so both the hydroxylation
and all in addition
the end of the aliphatic
chain in the cholesterols
need to be converted
to a carboxyl group
so both the hydroxylation
and carboxylation
of the cholesterol precursor
in order to increase
the solubility of the
bio salts make them
much easier to dissolve
in water environment
again bio acids are
mainly synthesizing liver
and directly from
cholesterols and two different
forms of bio salts colic
acid and kinodeoxycholic
acid and they are also
called primary bio
acid it right the hydroxylation
step of cholesterol
that catalyzed by
the enzyme 7-alpha
hydroxylase right seven
it referred to the carbon
number seven right here
this one and this one
this enzyme as you
catalyze the re-limiting
step right so therefore
you can regulate 7-alpha
hydroxylase so um the
primary the two primary
bioacids so once they
get into the intestines
they actually get
can be converted
by some of the
enzyme from bacteria
into a different form of
molecule and these are
called a secondary
bioacid right and if you
look the secondary bio
acid you can see that they
both lose the hydroxyl
group at carbon 7 and
you know they obviously
going to be more hydrophobic
right so therefore the
secondary biosolids
are less soluble than
the primary biosolids
In addition,
the primary biosol can be
conjugated with immunoacid
glycine or taurine, which
is a metabolite of cysteine.
So the conjugation of
either glycine or taurine
to the colic acid generating
glycocholic acid or
taurine colic acid right
as you noted that the colic
acid the pka is around six
but conjugation of glycine
and change the pka to
around four and conjugation
to a taurine and lower the
pKa to two right and this
is a really a big advantage
because in the intestines
the pH environment is about
six right so therefore
these two conjugated
biosolids and most likely
in a large majority in the
salt forms right right,
and therefore make them
better detergent because make
it more soluble in aqueous
solution. So therefore,
the conjugated by
salts, they are better
detergent and then
more efficient
in terms of emulsify
different lipids.
All right, so here summarize
the bio salts metabolism,
right. As we mentioned,
the bowel cell that's
secreted into the intestines,
a large majority of
them can be reabsorbed
and eventually returned to
the liver. And the whole
cycle is called enteral,
enteral, referred to a
prefix for intestine,
hepatic liver, enteral
hepatic circulation.
And, you know, because the
liver is the major site
to synthesize bile acid,
and obviously for certain
liver disease, the function
of liver is compromised.
And therefore you have reduced
amount of bile acid synthesis,
right?
And because certain amount
of bile acid can be excreted
through the feces, right?
So this could be a strategy,
or go through the enterohepatic
cycle, get reabsorbed
back in by liver. So this
could be a good strategy
if you could trap the bile
salts in the intestines.
For example, if you treat
the patient with the bile
salt sequestration,
colistaramine, right and that
can trap certain amount
of bile salts in the
intestines and and slow down
the enterohepatic circulation
and therefore reduce the
amount of cholesterols
right and also mentioned
some of the dietary fibers
can also reduce the
reabsorption of bile salts
so finally um there's
a new clinical issue
related to the imbalance
of the component
of for the bios right
again bios is made
up of cholesterol
it's very hydrophobic
and also phospholipid and
bile source both of them
are amphipathic molecules
again for antipatic molecule
they have a polar heads
you know make them easy to
dissolve into water and
hydro hydrophobic tails
combine to the hydrophobic
molecule if it fish it more
efficiently but for whatever
reason if you have more
cholesterol in the bios
right so that's going to tilt
the balance of the hydrophobic
molecule and hydrophilic
molecule right and
make the whole bio more
hydrophobic and that could
lead to the precipitates of
some of these hydrophilic
molecules right therefore
producing the stones in the
gallbladder this the disease
is called coli lithiasis
right you know because
the patient has too much
stones in their gallbladder
all right so here's the
final summary slides uh
you need to understand
uh a key concept right
and also need to understand
the normal or physiological
function of cholesterol
bile acid and which step
is the re-limiting step
and what an enzyme that
catalyzing the really many
steps because these are
the step that used to
regulate cholesterol and bowel
acid biosynthesis I
obviously familiar
yourself with a different
clinical correlation
all right so that's the end of
the lecture thank you very much